Miguel Ángel Castañeda Martínez

(+52) 55-3422-3103 | miguel.castama@outlook.com | LinkedIn | GitHub | Portfolio

SUMMARY

I am a data scientist experienced in manufacturing processes, financial services, and retail industry. My specialization covers end-to-end data science solutions from data engineering to end-user dashboards and storytelling. I'm interested on professional challenges involving Machine Learning and Statistical Modeling.

EXPERIENCE

Havas Media Group. Mexico City, MX. Feb 2024 – present.

Lead Data Scientist.

El Puerto de Liverpool. Mexico City, MX. Sep 2023 – Feb 2024.

Data Scientist.

- Developed an anomaly detection system for Liverpool's purchasing team, unveiling \$600 million MXN worth of stock in alert status. This also served as a KPI which led to define guidelines and best practices within future purchases.
- Designed an estimator for Liverpool's website, quantifying the effect of making a product visible for online sales. This provided the business team with valuable insights to define a strategy to maximize online sales effectiveness.

Instituto Nacional de Transparencia y Acceso a la Información, Mexico City, MX. Oct 2022 – May 2023.

Volunteer Data Scientist.

- Increased visibility of INAI's trending topics by implementing an alert system based on Google search trends, which helped INAI's operators detect attention topics up to 2 days prior to a ticket in the CRM system.
- Integrated a database with INAI related web searches by monitoring Google Trends through web-scrapping technics.
- Coded a natural language processor of INAI's CRM data to cluster search topics to feed the scrapper above.

Procesos Pross, Mexico City, MX.

Project Manager, Mar 2022 – Ago 2022.

- Designed and led the implementation of a Modularized Record Keeping System (MRKS) to replace legacy processes, increasing integration speed of client requirements by 40%.
- Executed the MRKS Proof of Concept with 5% of the costumers, setting a benchmark for IT to build the architecture.

Compliance Analyst, Apr 2021 – Mar 2022.

- Implemented a system for clock-in and clock-out from home office, gathering data for employee timeliness performance.
- Architected a requests platform with average rate of 50 requests a week, generating data for employee satisfaction metrics.

Bilstein Shock Absorbers, Hamilton, OH, US. Aug 2019 – Feb 2020.

Manufacturing Process Plan Intern.

Improved quality processes by analyzing data of given machines, scoring 100% in the quality assurance tests.

<u>UNAM Motorsports – Formula SAE</u>, Mexico City, MX.

Team Principal, Aug 2018 – Jul 2019.

• Led an interdisciplinary team to design, build, test, and compete with a Formula type racecar in a series of international competitions, finishing as the best Latin-American team in FSAE Lincoln 2019.

Team Member, Aug 2015 – Jul 2018.

Participated in the FSAE 2016, 2017, 2018 Design Series, progressively gaining responsibilities from Mechanical Designer
up to Design & Manufacturing Principal, where I led the engineering development of the vehicle.

Miguel Ángel Castañeda Martínez

(+52) 55-3422-3103 | miguel.castama@outlook.com | LinkedIn | GitHub | Portfolio

SKILLS

Spanish and English fluent in speaking and writing.

- Cloud & big data: GCP, Databricks, PySpark
- Data science: Python, R Software, SQL, BigQuery
- ML & DL Frameworks: ScikitLearn, TensorFlow
- BI: PowerBI, Looker, Shiny, Streamlit
- Bayesian inference: Stan
- Frameworks: Flask

ARTICLES

• A journey through Mexico City public cycling service (Ecobici). Nexos Magazine, Sep – 2023.

EDUCATION

- MSc. in Data Science. ITAM, Aug 2022 Dec 2023.
- Grad. Cert. in Data Science & ML applied to Financial Markets. ITAM, Aug 2021 Apr 2022.
- BSc. in Mechanical Engineering, top 12%. UNAM School of Engineering, Aug 2014 May 2019.